<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
			<channel>
				<title>Clagnut</title>
				<link>http://clagnut.com/</link>
				<atom:link href="http://clagnut.com/feeds/fullposts.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
				<description>A blog by Richard Rutter. Root through a heap of web design and development stuff and a few other tasty morsels. (latest 5 posts in full)</description>
				<language>en-gb</language>
				<copyright>Copyright 2003-2014, Richard Rutter</copyright>
				<webMaster>rich@clagnut.com (Richard Rutter)</webMaster>
				<managingEditor>rich@clagnut.com (Richard Rutter)</managingEditor>
				<image>
					<url>http://clagnut.com/images/clagnut_rss.png</url>
					<link>http://clagnut.com/</link>
					<title>Clagnut</title>
					<width>88</width>
					<height>31</height>
				</image>
		<item>
			<pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2014 17:36:19 PST</pubDate>
			<title>In conversation with Brighton station about CCTV</title>
			<link>http://clagnut.com/blog/2374/</link>
			<guid>http://clagnut.com/blog/2374/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago I was stuck at Brighton railway station, watching trains get delayed and eventually cancelled. In the end I gave up waiting for carriage to take me to my meeting in London, and went back to <a href="http://68middle.st">the office</a>. But while I sat on the concourse I noticed &#8211; not for the first time &#8211; the sheer amount of <abbr>CCTV</abbr>, cameras, and various surveillance devices in plain view all around the station.</p>

	<p><figure class="fullbleed"><img src="http://clagnut.com/images/cctv.jpg" alt="Montage of photos" /><figcaption>A selection of the surveillance in Brighton station</figcaption></figure>

	<p>In this day and age, and especially here in the <abbr>UK</abbr> where we have <a href="http://www.wired.co.uk/magazine/archive/2010/05/start/investigation-a-sharp-focus-on-cctv">the most <abbr>CCTV</abbr> per capita in Europe</a>, we as society have come to expect and seemingly accept having a few cameras in public places like railway stations. Personally I&#8217;m very dubious about the efficacy of <abbr>CCTV</abbr> as means of crime prevention, I&#8217;m even less convinced about the cost effectiveness &#8211; <acronym title='Freedom of Information'>FOI</acronym> requests reveal that one installed camera costs around &#163;20,000. And I&#8217;m perturbed further still about where that footage goes and how it is used. </p>

	<p>Anyway, I saw all those cameras (there are 28 in the photo) and was a bit bored, so I did what any good citizen would do. I tweeted about it:</p>

	<dl><dt>&#8207;clagnut <a href="https://twitter.com/clagnut/status/431718797771173888">9:19am, 7 Feb 2014</a></dt><dd><abbr>CCTV</abbr> gone mad in Brighton station (there are 3 banks like this). Is this really acceptable &#64;southernrailuk? <a href="http://pic.twitter.com/YstXebY2y8">pic.twitter.com/YstXebY2y8</a> </dd></dl><p>Soon after, I got a reply. Turns out <a href="https://twitter.com/brightonstation">Brighton Station</a> has got a Twitter account.</p>

	<dl><dt>&#8207;&#8207;@brightonstation <a href="https://twitter.com/clagnut/status/431718797771173888">9:44am, 7 Feb 2014</a></dt>
<dd>.@clagnut I guess it depends if your loved ones have been assaulted or not and you want to catch the scoundrel</dd>
</dl><p>And <a href="https://twitter.com/brightonstation/status/431725032638009344">the conversation</a> continued as only Twitter can. It got a bit interesting here and there.</p>

	<dl><dt>&#8207;@clagnut</dt>
<dd>@brightonstation Proportion. Privacy.</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@clagnut</dt>
<dd>@brightonstation Also, how many convictions have there been thanks to the <abbr>CCTV</abbr>? Have crime rates decreased since their installation?</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@Binarytales</dt>
<dd>@clagnut I believe they are facial recognition cameras focused on the gates. Not that that makes it okay.</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@brightonstation</dt>
<dd>.@clagnut if you look, they are mostly focused one per gate, to catch naughty ticket people/protect staff and pax from unfounded allegations</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@clagnut</dt>
<dd>@brightonstation That might be why <strong>you</strong> use the cameras, but what happens to the recordings? We&#8217;re given good reason to paranoid recently.</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@Belladax</dt>
<dd>@brightonstation &#64;clagnut ah, that makes more sense. Revenue protection, not really looking out for our &#8216;loved ones&#8217;.</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@brightonstation</dt>
<dd>@Belladax If you were assaulted on station and then they said they had removed cameras to protect the innocent, would you be happier?</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@Belladax</dt>
<dd>@brightonstation I absolutely appreciate the need for security, but wld hope enough staff on duty to help. As &#64;clagnut says, bit excessive</dd>
<dt>Brighton Station</dt>
<dd>@Belladax Realistically, to get a prosecution in 2014 you need good clear facial cctv, word of staff not enough for <abbr>CPS</abbr> usually</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@Belladax</dt>
<dd>@brightonstation good to know, thanks. You get a lot of assaults?</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@brightonstation</dt>
<dd>@Belladax I have 16mil people through me a year, and at weekends in summer a lot of boozed up landlubbers come down to party too hard!</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@brightonstation</dt>
<dd>@clagnut The station is private property and there are signs saying there is cctv. I bet your local newsagent has more cameras per sq foot</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@ShirtlessKirk</dt>
<dd>@brightonstation &#64;clagnut Well hidden signs. Plus, Waterloo has the most cameras of any terminus yet doesn&#8217;t have any gate-facing ones&#8230;</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@clagnut</dt>
<dd>@brightonstation Specious argument. My newsagent can&#8217;t track my movements and isn&#8217;t connected to national infrastructure.</dd>
<dt>&#8207;@bh_community</dt>
<dd>&#64;clagnut never heard of <a href="http://www.police-life.co.uk/products/crime-fighting-scheme-engages-public-monitoring-of-cctv">internet eyes</a>?</dd></dl><p>I should probably add that I&#8217;ve no idea if <a href="http://twitter.com/brightonstation">@brightonstation</a> actually speaks on behalf of Southern Rail &#8211; the <a href="https://twitter.com/aegirthor/status/434028753434710016">general opinion</a> is that the account is an enthusiast, rather than an official account.</p>
<p><a href='http://clagnut.com/blog/2374/'>Read or add comments</a></p>]]></description>
			<category domain="http://clagnut.com/archive/brighton/">Brighton</category>
			<category domain="http://clagnut.com/archive/politics/">Politics</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Brighton,War">Brighton,War</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/and">and</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Politics,CCTV,privacy,station,Twitter">Politics,CCTV,privacy,station,Twitter</category>
		</item>
		<item>
			<pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 23:15:01 PST</pubDate>
			<title>A new year, a new design</title>
			<link>http://clagnut.com/blog/2373/</link>
			<guid>http://clagnut.com/blog/2373/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[<p>To my surprise, Clagnut.com was last redesigned in <a href=\"/blog/2183/\">September 2008</a> &#8211; that\&#8217;s getting on for 6 years ago. Well, that\&#8217;s all changed now, as will be evident to you, unless you&#8217;re viewing this in a <abbr title=\"Really Simple Sydication\" class=\"smcp\"><abbr title='Really Simple Syndication'>RSS</abbr></abbr> reader (remember those?).</p><p>I\&#8217;m still pleased with the 2008 design &#8211; I think it held up reasonably well &#8211; but it was fixed-width, designed with the grid first, and starting to feel a bit \&#8217;small\&#8217;. I felt the site needed a new design, created from the typography outwards, responsive from the beginning and elegant on huge as well as tiny screens. That and I really want to write more, so I felt &#8211; in true procrastination style &#8211; that I needed a new design with a lovely reading experience to encourage that writing to happen.</p>                <figure class=\"inline\"><a href=\"http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/389955468X?tag=jalfrezi-21\"><img src=\"/images/designingnews_180.png\" alt=\"Book cover showing similar colours and typographic treatment\" /></a><figcaption>Front cover of Designing News</figcaption></figure><h3>Inspiration</h3><p>After a few false starts to the redesign, I came across a fabulous book, <a href=\"http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/389955468X?tag=jalfrezi-21\"><cite>Designing News</cite></a> by <a href=\"http://www.FrancescoFranchi.com\">Francesco Franchi</a> and was hooked. It\&#8217;s not hard to see that I ended up unashamedly using the book\&#8217;s front cover as a basis for my graphic design. I hope Francesco can forgive me for butchering his fine work and adapting it for my own purposes.</figure><h3>Typography</h3><p>Where my design is different to Franchi\&#8217;s is in the choice of type. In all of those false starts, I had been trying to combine a high contrast serif font, set large for headings, with a sensibly sized contemporary sans for the body text. More and more I found myself drawn to the same two typefaces.  <a href=\"http://typejockeys.com/\">Michael Hochleitner</a>\&#8217;s <a href=\"http://fontdeck.com/typeface/ingeborg/\">Ingeborg</a> for the headings, and <a href=\"http://fontdeck.com/typeface/akagi/\">Akagi</a> by <a href=\"http://positype.com/\">Neil Summerour</a> for the body text.</p><p>To my eyes, Akagi and Ingeborg have common typographic ancestry. They both have a vertical stress with a sturdy, rational approach tempered by a certain glamour &#8211; the very definition of substance and style. The two typefaces have similar flourishes such as the eye to the lower case g, and matching letterforms such as the lowercase a and y. The low-contrast Akagi Medium works extremely well on screens, and juxtaposes really well with the high contrast, almost fat-face Ingeborg Heavy. It works for me. As you might expect, both fonts are served up by <a href=\"http://fontdeck.com/\">Fontdeck</a>.</p><figure><img src=\"/images/ingeborg-akagi.png\" alt=\"Comparison of the two fonts\" style=\"opacity:0.9\" /><figcaption>Ingeborg Heavy / Akagi Medium</figcaption></figure>                 <h3>Responsiveness</h3>               <figure class=\"inline\"><img src=\"/images/responsive-design-view.png\" alt=\"Firefox Responsive Design View\" title=\"Firefox Responsive Design View\" /><figcaption>Responsive Design View</figcaption></figure><p> I\&#8217;ve used responsive design techniques to help the site be nicely readable on lots of devices. At the time of writing, there are nine break points, including height as well as width. All the media queries are set in <code>em</code> rather than <code>px</code> as the break points are designed around where the design <em>breaks</em> rather than an arbitrary screen size. The <a href=\"https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Tools/Responsive_Design_View\">Firefox Responsive Design View</a> proved invaluable before an actual device testing on the <a href=\"http://clearleft.com/testlab/\">Clearleft test lab</a> was involved.</figure><p>I\&#8217;ve put together a kind of <a href=\"/styles\">style guide</a>, mostly as a check that all likely mark-up is styled appropriately. While the site has not been widely tested, it should be fine on all modern browsers. Please <a href=\"/about#contact\">let me know</a> if you come across any problems. You can also read more production details in the <a href=\"/colophon/\">colophon</a>.</p> <h3>Home Page</h3><p>The home page is now slightly more dashboard-like, in that I wanted to include a lot of \&#8217;live\&#8217; content from my presence elsewhere on the web. So interspersed among the blog posts are photos from Flickr, tweets, music scrobbled via Last.fm, extracts from Kennedy app, and my current Jam.</p><h3>Blog Post Pages</h3><p>The reading experience of the blog posts should be better now, and they can now handle much larger images and tables. I\&#8217;m using machine tags to pull in photos from Flickr where relevant. The related posts should soon become more relevant too. I\&#8217;m planning on introducing a calendar view to the archive, but for you\&#8217;ll have to make do with paging through months and categories.</p> <h4>What No Comments?</h4>    <p>The site is built on my homemade <abbr class=\"smcp\"><abbr>CMS</abbr></abbr> written in <abbr class=\"smcp\"><abbr>PHP</abbr></abbr> and <span class=\"smcp\">M</span>y<span class=\"smcp\"><abbr>SQL</abbr></span>. Unfortunately, since <a href=\"/blog/2272/\">the great database disappearance</a> comments have been turned off. I might reinstate them at some point in the future, but for now you can <a href=\"/about#contact\">contact me</a> by other methods. The whole site is now hosted by <a href=\"http://my.vidahost.com/aff.php?aff=1321\">Vidahost</a> who have a simpler and more reliable database backup system than Joyent clearly did.</p>
<p><a href='http://clagnut.com/blog/2373/'>Read or add comments</a></p>]]></description>
			<category domain="http://clagnut.com/archive/site_news/">Clagnut news</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/ClagnutNews,">ClagnutNews,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/typography,">typography,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/responsive,">responsive,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/redesign,">redesign,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/RWD,">RWD,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Vidahost,">Vidahost,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Firefox,">Firefox,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/PHP/MySQL">PHP/MySQL</category>
		</item>
		<item>
			<pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2012 20:37:10 PST</pubDate>
			<title>UK Museums on the Web 2012</title>
			<link>http://clagnut.com/blog/2371/</link>
			<guid>http://clagnut.com/blog/2371/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://lanyrd.com/2012/ukmw12/" title="on Lanyrd"><abbr>UK</abbr> Museums on the Web</a> is a one day conference organised by the <a href="http://museumscomputergroup.org.uk">Museums Computer Group</a> and held in the lecture theatre of the <a href="http://www.wellcomecollectionconference.org/">Wellcome Collection</a>. Representatives from museums and other organisations in the sector shared their experiences over the past year and beyond. Tweets tagged #ukmw12 on the day are <a href="http://www.tweetarchivist.com/armchair_caver/7" title="#ukmw12">archived on TweetArchivist</a>. These are some scattered notes transcribed from scribbles in my notebook.</p>

	<p>This year the conference was dubbed &#8216;Strategically Digital&#8217;. It was a fascinating, insightful day with some really engaging speakers. The format worked well, with three lots of three presentations on a theme followed by a brief panel discussion with Q&#38;A. Coincidentally this a format Clearleft will be employing at our forthcoming Responsive Day Out.</p>

	<p><a href="http://twitter.com/armchair_caver"><strong>Paul Rowe</strong></a>, <abbr>CEO</abbr> of <a href="http://www.vernonsystems.com">Vernon Systems</a>, and with the strongest New Zealand accent I&#8217;ve ever heard, gave us a typically witty keynote. He encouraged everyone to share their content and make it available everywhere. <abbr>API</abbr>s, Commons media, and loose licenses to the fore.</p>

	<p><strong>Andrew Lewis</strong>, Digital Content Delivery Manager (I like that this role exists) from the <a href="http://www.vam.ac.uk">Victoria &#38; Albert Museum</a> talked about the gradual transformation to becoming a digital first organisation. He described how that necessitated a brand new, top-down, governance structure to ensure consistency and longevity of technologies, and to avoid duplication of ideas across departments. Digital, he said, does not respect departmental boundaries.</p>

	<p><a href="http://twitter.com/richbs"><strong>Rich Barrett-Small</strong></a>, lead web developer at the V&#38;A, followed up with his view &#8216;from a dark place&#8217;. He used the analogy that his team worked as an Agile barrel tumbling through the waterfall processes of an inherently un-agile organisation. He urged museums not to embark on any digital project longer than 3 months, or if it really needs to be longer than that, deliver something tangible after each three months.</p>

	<p>In the audience, Stuart Dempster from <a href="http://www.jisc.ac.uk">Jisc</a> (which works on behalf of <abbr>UK</abbr> higher &#38; further education to champion the use of digital technologies and is responsible for <abbr>JANET</abbr>) made the point that part of digital strategy should be managing your organisation&#8217;s online reputation. At it simplest, that means &#8211; among other things &#8211; replying to tweets and answering comments on <a href="http://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g186338-d187677-Reviews-Tate_Modern-London_England.html">TripAdvisor</a>, and making changes in the real world if those comments highlight areas needing improvement. Stuart also mentioned that the <a href="http://www.hlf.org.uk">Heritage Lottery Fund</a> has finally agreed that digital output from a cultural institution is something it is <a href="http://www.hlf.org.uk/HowToApply/furtherresources/Pages/Newdigitalpolicyandrequirementsfordigitaloutputs.aspx">prepared to fund</a>.</p>

	<p>Charlotte Holmes from the <a href="http://www.museumsassociation.org/">Museums Association</a>, which she said represents museums and their suppliers, talked about <abbr title="continuing professsional development"><abbr>CPD</abbr></abbr> with respect to digital. She said they require more mentors to help people achieve the professional qualifications they offer (<a href="http://www.museumsassociation.org/professional-development/associateship-of-the-museums-association"><abbr>AMA</abbr>s</a>). It seems to me that people outside of the sector itself, a <a href="http://clearleft.com/">digital design agency</a> for example, could be able to help in this regard, although some business development opportunities in return would probably be desirable. It was hard to tell if they was any desire for either.</p>

	<p><a href="https://twitter.com/TomGrinsted">Tom Grinsted</a>, product manager of core mobile apps for the <a href="http://guardian.co.uk">Guardian</a> gave a brief but entertaining view of the rapidly changing face of digital audiences, or &#8220;How I learned that there&#8217;s no such thing as a digital consumer&#8221;. Which about sums it up. He showed that use of the Guardian iPad app peaks first thing in the morning, but not in the evening; whereas the website viewed on a tablet peaks in the evening but less so in the morning. The main takeaway being: when designing don&#8217;t partition people, partition actions; in other words there&#8217;s no such thing as a mobile user.</p>

	<p><a href="https://twitter.com/NickPoole1">Nick Poole</a>, <abbr>CEO</abbr> of the <a href="http://www.collectionstrust.org.uk/">Collections Trust</a> presented some pithy truths about creating digital resources:</p>


<ul>
	<li>access &#8800; value</li>
	<li>open access &#8800; lower sales</li>
	<li>digital &#8800; audience</li>

</ul>
	<p>Nick talked about determining the return on investment of providing a digital resource, not so much in financial terms but in terms of a cultural return. That linked perfectly into the next talk. <a href="http://twitter.com/SimonTanner">Simon Tanner</a> from the <a href="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/artshums/depts/ddh/">Department of Digital Humanities</a> at King&#8217;s College London talked passionately about Curation &#38; Impact for the Digital Age, with the emphasis very much on impact, which is akin to the &#8216;return&#8217; described by Nick in the previous talk.</p>

	<p>Simon defined impact as &#8220;the measurable outcomes arising from the existence of a digital resource that demonstrate a change in the life or life opportunities of the community for which the resource is intended.&#8221; Put simply, how does your digital presence affect people&#8217;s lives? Loads more details, including how to present a convincing evidence-based argument for digital resources are <a href="http://www.kdcs.kcl.ac.uk/innovation/impact.html">available for download</a> on the <abbr>KDCS</abbr> website.</p>

	<p><a href="https://twitter.com/clairey_ross">Claire Ross</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/shelfappeal">Jane Audas</a> talked about their experience trying to run digital R&#38;D with the <a href="http://www.iwm.org.uk">Imperial War Museums</a>. They came across similar difficulties to those highlighted by Rich Barrett-Small in trying to do Agile in a fundamentally non-agile environment. Long term outputs (5 years plus) with lots of stakeholders wanting to &#8216;sign off&#8217; does not map to a process of continuous iteration.</p>

	<p>Part of their project was enabling museum visitors to write comments on the exhibits using a kiosk next to the exhibit itself. A battle won was allowing for &#8216;radical trust&#8217; and the realisation that post moderation works: visitors may write inane comments, but never offensive ones. Oh, and <abbr>QR</abbr> codes don&#8217;t work.</p>

	<p>Mentioned in passing was the fascinating <a href="http://ww1.discovery.ac.uk/"><abbr>WW1</abbr> Discovery</a> project which aims to make resources about the Great War more discoverable, and find new and innovative ways to present this content for the benefit of education and research. Also cropping up was the <a href="http://www.google.com/culturalinstitute/#!home">Google Cultural Institute</a>, which I&#8217;ll admit I&#8217;d never come across, probably because while Google claims it is &#8220;building tools that make it simple to tell the stories of our diverse cultural heritage&#8221; it all looks very closed.</p>

	<p>The afore-mentioned Stuart Dempster was up next and quoted <a href="https://twitter.com/gnat&#8217;s">Nat Torkington</a> excellent article <a href="http://nathan.torkington.com/blog/2011/11/23/libraries-where-it-all-went-wrong/">Libraries &#8211; Where It All Went Wrong</a>. The choice bit being:</p>

	<blockquote><p>I look at the results of digitization projects, I find the shittiest websites on the planet.  It&#8217;s like a gallery spent all its money buying art and then just stuck the paintings in supermarket bags and leaned them against the wall.</p></blockquote>

	<p>Finally came <a href="katybeale">Katy Beale</a> from <a href="http://wearecaper.com/">Caper</a> who talked about a few of their fun ventures, including <a href="http://culturehackday.org.uk">Culture Hackday</a> and the <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com/">Happenstance</a> project, the <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com/james-bridle/">James Bridle</a> and <a href="http://happenstanceproject.com/natalia-buckley/">Natalia Buckley</a> part of which happened in Clearleft&#8217;s building.</p>

	<p>All in all it was a thoroughly interesting day, especially from one who is somewhat of an outsider, and I got to have some fascinating conversations in the break. I&#8217;m really looking forward to Clearleft working more with museums, galleries and others in this sector.</p>
<p><a href='http://clagnut.com/blog/2371/'>Read or add comments</a></p>]]></description>
			<category domain="http://clagnut.com/archive/information_design/">Information design</category>
			<category domain="http://clagnut.com/archive/conferences/">Conferences</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Conferences,">Conferences,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Information">Information</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/design,">design,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/museums,">museums,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/heritage">heritage</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/sector,">sector,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/ukmw12">ukmw12</category>
		</item>
		<item>
			<pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2012 09:40:58 PST</pubDate>
			<title>Something\&#8217;s missing around here</title>
			<link>http://clagnut.com/blog/2272/</link>
			<guid>http://clagnut.com/blog/2272/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[<p>You may have noticed that the most recent post on Clagnut (apart from this one) dates back almost exactly six years &#8211; to June 2006. That is due to a catastrophic database failure. I hope to rescue the missing 6 years over the coming weeks; there\&#8217;s quite a lot in the \<a href="http://wayback.archive.org/web/*/http://clagnut.com">WayBackMachine\</a> so that might be a good start. The comments are in there too, which would be as much of a sad loss as the blog posts themselves.</p>

	<p>So did I have a backup? Well obviously not, at least not a recent one. Files: yes. Database: no. So what happened to the database anyway? Good question, thanks for asking.</p>

	<p>It all started back in 2004 when I stumped up $200 for lifetime hosting with \&#8221;Textdrive (Going back in time)\&#8221;:http://web.archive.org/web/20051129024936/http://www.textdrive.com/ (I was a so-called <abbr>VC200</abbr>). \<a href="http://joyent.com">Joyent\</a> acquired Textdrive a few years later and honoured the lifetime hosting for <abbr>VC200</abbr> folk. Well since then we\&#8217;ve been stuck on what seems to be a wretchedly slow server (the dreaded \&#8217;One\&#8217; shared server), but heh you pay peanuts&#8230;.</p>

	<p>In fairness Joyent have tried pursuading me to move to one or other of their better services, but frankly they didn\&#8217;t exactly offer much help with that beyond a long set of daunting technical instructions. And so eventually payback came. \&#8217;One\&#8217; finally gave up the ghost and disppeared off the face of the Earth. Along with the files and databases I run for all my sites, including \<a href="http://clagnut.com/">Clagnut\</a> and \<a href="http://webtypography.net/">Web Typography\</a>. After a few days Joyent managed to reinstate all the files and databases apart from the \&#8217;clagnut\&#8217; database. It was gone without trace. Still at least they apologised:</p>

	<blockquote><p>I\&#8217;m very sorry about this. Our operations team have not been able to restore the \&#8217;clagnut\&#8217; database.</p></blockquote>

	<p>I\&#8217;ve now moved Clagnut over to \&#8221;Vidahost (Yes it\&#8217;s an affiliate link but I\&#8217;m happy to recommend them)\&#8221;:http://my.vidahost.com/aff.php?aff=1321 who, so far, seem very helpful. And my site is much faster too.</p>

	<h4>Update</h4>

	<p>I\&#8217;m gradually reinstating blog posts from the \<a href="http://wayback.archive.org/web/*/http://clagnut.com/">Internet Archive\</a>, so if you see some slightly odd and out-of-date things appearing, check the date on the post.</p>
<p><a href='http://clagnut.com/blog/2272/'>Read or add comments</a></p>]]></description>
			<category domain="http://clagnut.com/archive/site_news/">Clagnut news</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/ClagnutNews,">ClagnutNews,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Textdrive,">Textdrive,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/fail,">fail,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/hosting,">hosting,</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Vidahost">Vidahost</category>
		</item>
		<item>
			<pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2011 14:17:24 PST</pubDate>
			<title>Top Tunes 2010</title>
			<link>http://clagnut.com/blog/2354/</link>
			<guid>http://clagnut.com/blog/2354/</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[<figure><img src="http://clagnut.com/images/bestsongs2010.jpg" alt="Artwork of The Best Songs I Bought In 2010 Ever" /></figure>

	<p>So here it is again: the track listing to my annual compilation, &#8216;The Best Songs I Bought In 2010 Ever&#8217;. I&#8217;m quite pleased with this year. It all seems to flow nicely, and there&#8217;s a <em>bit</em> more variation than previous years.</p>

	<h3>The Best Songs I Bought In 2010 Ever</h3>

	<ol></p>
	<p><li><cite>Throwing Bones</cite> by The Phantom Band from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B001KKRD54/jalfrezi-21/">Checkmate Savage</a></li>
<li><cite>A Rumour In Africa</cite> by Errors from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B003334SMM/jalfrezi-21/">Come Down With Me</a></li>
<li><cite>We Have Love</cite> by Hot Chip from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B003WZ2Q8O/jalfrezi-21/">One Life Stand</a></li>
<li><cite>Stress Position</cite> by Steve Mason from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B003CWRNOY/jalfrezi-21/">Boys Outside</a></li>
<li><cite>The Pact (I&#8217;ll Be Your Fever)</cite> by Villagers from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B003D85E6Q/jalfrezi-21/">Becoming A Jackal</a></li>
<li><cite>Treat Me Like Your Mother</cite> by The Dead Weather from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B0029U2GHE/jalfrezi-21/">Horehound</a></li>
<li><cite>It&#8217;s The Weekend</cite> by Jason Lytle from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B001WAVUO2/jalfrezi-21/">Yours Truly, The Commuter</a></li>
<li><cite>Sigourney Weaver</cite> by John Grant from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B00369K2SM/jalfrezi-21/">Queen Of Denmark</a></li>
<li><cite>Suffragette Suffragette</cite> by Everything Everything from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B0036ORISO/jalfrezi-21/">Man Alive</a></li>
<li><cite>Evening Of Swing (Has Been Cancelled)</cite> by Half Man Half Biscuit from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B00163JHAO/jalfrezi-21/"><abbr><abbr>CSI</abbr></abbr>: Ambleside</a></li>
<li><cite>Last Broadcast</cite> by The Soundcarriers from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B003LZ38QE/jalfrezi-21/">Celeste</a></li>
<li><cite>White Table</cite> by Delta Spirit from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B003EYEFC8/jalfrezi-21/">History From Below</a></li>
<li><cite>Hallogallo</cite> by Neu! from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B000A87W94/jalfrezi-21/">Neu 1</a></li>
<li><cite>Paradise Circus</cite> by Massive Attack from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B002ZPIC1M/jalfrezi-21/">Heligoland</a></li>
<li><cite>All To All</cite> by Broken Social Scene from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B003A2J984/jalfrezi-21/">Forgiveness Rock Record</a></li>
<li><cite>Pure As Snow (Trails Of The Winter Storm)</cite> by Mono from the album <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/B001P5C0XO/jalfrezi-21/">Hymn To The Immortal Wind</a></li></p>

	<p></ol>
	<p>I realise I&#8217;ve missed out compilations for 2008 and 2009. These exist so for completeness I&#8217;ll post them up in due course.</p>
<p><a href='http://clagnut.com/blog/2354/'>Read or add comments</a></p>]]></description>
			<category domain="http://clagnut.com/archive/music/">Music</category>
<category domain="http://technorati.com/tag/Music,TopTunes,compilation,2010">Music,TopTunes,compilation,2010</category>
		</item>
	</channel>
		</rss>